<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some papers given in by the Commissioners of the Parliament of Scotland, to the Honourable Houses of the Parliament of England in answer to their votes of the 24. of September 1646. Concerning the disposing of His Majesties person.</title>
            <title>Proceedings. 1646-9</title>
            <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A92612</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S1344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R232198</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99897676</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99897676</idno>
            <idno type="VID">137407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A92612)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 137407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2519:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some papers given in by the Commissioners of the Parliament of Scotland, to the Honourable Houses of the Parliament of England in answer to their votes of the 24. of September 1646. Concerning the disposing of His Majesties person.</title>
                  <title>Proceedings. 1646-9</title>
                  <author>Scotland. Convention of Estates.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Evan Tyler, printer to the Kings most excellent Majestie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:137407:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME PAPERS Given in by the COMMISSIONERS of the PARLIAMENT of <hi>SCOTLAND, To the Honourable</hi> HOUSES <hi>of the Parliament of ENGLAND:</hi> In Anſwer to their VOTES of the 24. <hi>of September</hi> 1646. CONCERNING The diſpoſing of His MAJESTIES <hi>PERSON.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>EDINBURGH: <hi>Printed by</hi> Evan Tyler, <hi>Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſtie.</hi> 1646.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:137407:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:137407:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:137407:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:137407:3"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Aving received the Votes of both Hou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, dated the 24 of September, concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ning the diſpoſing of the Kings Perſon as both Houſes of Parliament ſhall think fit. Although we judge (as in charity we ought) that it is not the meaning and intention of the Honourable Houſes, to claime or aſſume to themſelves the whole and ſole power to diſpoſe of his Majeſties Perſon, which is known to be a matter, as of high, ſo of common and equall concernment to both Kingdoms: Yet leſt by our ſilence the right and intereſt of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould be prejudiced; and leſt that ſenſe of thoſe Votes, which many have apprehended and expreſſed, ſhould miniſter occaſion of miſ-underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and difference between the Kingdoms, according to the deſires and hopes of our common enemies; We have judged it neceſſary, with that freedom, candor, and plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe which becometh Brethren, to repreſent our thoughts concerning this great buſineſſe, to both Houſes.</p>
            <p>We do acknowledge, that as Poſitively the Houſes of Parliament have as much power in diſpoſing of the Kings Perſon as any one Parliament hath or can have, to diſpoſe of a King who hath more free Kingdoms then one; So Negatively none ought or may diſpoſe of his Majeſties Perſon, without, or againſt their conſent. The like we ſuppoſe, will be mutually acknowledged in reference to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> It being a fundamentall Right and Liberty of either Kingdom, That none can juſtly
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:137407:4"/>(without their own conſent) impede or reſtrain the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of their King from coming amongſt them, and doing the duties of a King unto them: And in both theſe Senſes we acquieſce in the Vote of the Honourable Houſes.</p>
            <p>But if the Vote ſhould be meant or made uſe of as re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictive to the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and excluſive of the Parliament of <hi>Scotland;</hi> Or, as if the two Houſes were to diſpoſe of the Perſon of the King, by their ſingle and ſole authority, without the conſent and concurrence of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland;</hi> We truſt this ſenſe is as far from the thoughts of both Houſes, as it is from juſtice and equity: the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> having as much inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the Perſon of the King of <hi>Scotland,</hi> as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>England</hi> hath in the Perſon of the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and the Perſon being but one, both Kingdoms muſt needs ſhare equally in that joynt intereſt. Neither hath the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> any more power to diſpoſe of the perſon of this King of <hi>Scotland</hi> being in <hi>England,</hi> then the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath to diſpoſe of the Perſon of this King of <hi>England</hi> if he were in <hi>Scotland:</hi> And as the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> might juſtly conceive their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt and power to be greatly prejudiced, if the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould claim the ſole power to diſpoſe of His Majeſties Perſon being in <hi>Scotland</hi> (and conſequently if they ſhall ſo think fit to reſtrain his Perſon from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Houſes of Parliament when the neceſſary affairs of this Kingdom require his preſence) So we cannot but in juſtice expect to be dealt with by the Honourable Houſes, as they would have us in like caſes to deal with them.</p>
            <p>Although what we have now expreſſed might be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, as to our ſenſe of the Vote; Yet it ſhall not be
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:137407:4"/>ſuperfluous but very expedient, that we further clear our ſelves and our reall intentions, in that which we firſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in our Paper of the 11. of Auguſt, Concerning a joynt conſultation and reſolution of both Kingdoms, what is next to be done in reference to the King. Which motion we now reſume to be ſtill inſiſted upon: For the queſtion is not, whether the Houſes of Parliament, or the Scots Army ſhall diſpoſe of the perſon of the King in <hi>England.</hi> Our Army claimeth no power to diſpoſe of his Majeſties Perſon. And as they could not refuſe to receive him when he came amongſt them; So they are ready to obey and ſubmit to the joynt reſolutions of both Kingdoms concerning his Majeſtie. Neither is the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which of the two Kingdoms ſhall truſt the other with the preſent reſidence of the Kings Perſon, till he be diſpoſed of by the conſent and agreement of both. Let it be far from both Kingdoms, that the former mutuall confidence, ſhould now turn to a mutuall diffidence: And let not a bleſſing from heaven be expected upon either of the Nations, which continueth not faithfull to the other, according to the Covenant; Our confidence in the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Juſtice, Loyaltie, and Faithfulneſſe of the Honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Houſes is ſuch, that whenſoever the King ſhall be willing to return unto them, and they willing to receive him, we ſhall not make the leaſt impediment, but give our cheerfull conſent. Leaſt of all is the queſtion concerning any Priviledge or Power of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> or any Law, Liberty, or practiſe of this Kingdom, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of their King. It is not our meaning to controvert what in that kinde they may do, or at any time have done according to their Laws (which are beſt known to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) for their good and ſafety, without the leaſt ſhadow
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:137407:5"/>of any dependencie upon another Kingdom. But withall we deſire it may be remembred, that this is to be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred equally to the power and priviledge of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Scotland.</hi> We do not meddle with any of the ſingle or proper Rights, Priviledges, or Laws of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, more then we would have our Brethren to meddle with ours. It is one thing what the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> might have done in another Cauſe or Warre, before their engagements by the Covenant and Treaties with the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland:</hi> It is another thing what ought to be done after ſuch conditions and tyes impoſed by nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Kingdom upon the other, but by both joyntly upon themſelves, and as mutuall Obligations, both to God, and each to other: Although we might alſo go further back than to the Covenant and Treaties, and plead the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and equall intereſt of the Kingdoms, in their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Head and Soveraign, ever ſince they were ſo united, as may ſufficiently appear, even by ſome inſtances in his Majeſties time who now reigns over us. It may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred (as to the intereſt of <hi>Scotland</hi>) that when his Majeſtie was firſt invited and deſired to come into that Kingdome to be Crowned, It was repreſented by the Lords of his Majeſties Privie Councell in <hi>England,</hi> that the great affairs of this Kingdom could hardly diſpence with his Majeſties going to <hi>Scotland:</hi> And therefore that either hee might receive his Crown of <hi>Scotland</hi> by a Vicegerent there, or that it might be ſent hither unto him. Likeas, this preſent Parliament when the King went laſt into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to ſettle the Peace of that Kingdome, did earneſtly deſire and preſſe, that Hee might not goe, but that hee might ſtay here for the urgent affairs of this Kingdome. But both in the one caſe and in the other, the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:137407:5"/>intereſt of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> was preſerved: And as it was moſt neceſſary, that His Majeſtie ſhould goe into that Kingdome for receiving that Crown, ſo His Majeſty found it expedient to goe thither for the ſettling of Peace. It may alſo be remembred (as to the intereſt of <hi>England</hi>) that the Engliſh Nobility both at the <hi>Birks Anno</hi> 1639, and at <hi>York</hi> 1640 (whoſe letters to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe are yet extant and to be ſeen) And this Parliament <hi>Anno</hi> 1641 did claime an intereſt to ſee and know our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands propoſed to the King, that neither His Majeſty nor themſelves might be hereby prejudiced.</p>
            <p>But the preſent queſtion needeth not goe ſo farre upon a back trade: Whatſoever the joynt intereſt of the Kingdomes was formerly, it is without controverſie now much more conjoyned. And unleſſe we lay aſide the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, Treaties, Declaration of both Kingdomes, and three years conjunction in this warre, Neither the one Kingdome nor the other, muſt now look back what they might have done ſingly before ſuch a ſtrict Union; but look forward, what is fitteſt to be done by both joyntly for the common good of both, and for the ends of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, which both are oblieged joyntly to proſecute and promote. So that the true and proper queſtion in this conjuncture of affairs, is, whether both Kingdoms have not a joynt and common intereſt, in diſpoſing of the King of both, for the good of both, and that His Majeſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought not to be diſpoſed of by either Kingdome ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly. Much might be ſaid for this joynt way, and againſt a divided way, from the nature of all aſſociations, and the common rules of equity obſerved between perſons, ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or nations, which have a joynt intereſt in the ſame Perſon, Parent, Maſter, Servant, Or in the ſame thing,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:137407:6"/>inheritance, lands, houſe, ſtock, or the like. In which caſes, one of the parties aſſociated, may not without the conſent of the other, diſpoſe of that which is common, eſpecially if it be a common Perſon, and leaſt of all if it be a Perſon of chiefeſt eminency or concernment: For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a common thing may be divided, and to each party his proper ſhare aſſigned, yet one individuall Perſon doth not admit of a partition, and ſo requireth the greater Union and conjunction of Councels in the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of it. And as reaſons may be drawn from the nature of all aſſociations; ſo eſpecially from the nature of ours in the ſolemn League and Covenant, the Title, Narrative, Articles and concluſion of it, do all along linke together the intereſt of the Kingdomes, in this common cauſe ſo much concerning the glory of God, their own ſafety U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion and Peace, and the honour and happineſſe of the King and his poſterity; which ends of the Covenant, both Parliaments aſwell as other Subjects of both Kingdoms, have oblieged themſelves joyntly and mutually to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, according to their power, and to continue zealouſly and conſtantly therein all the dayes of their lives, againſt all oppoſition; And to aſſiſt and defend all thoſe that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into this League and Covenant in the maintaining and purſuing thereof, and never ſuffer themſelves to be divided directly or indirectly from this bleſſed Union and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction. So that the ends of the Covenant (upon which the diſpoſall of the King muſt needs have a ſtrong influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) are not to be proſecuted by the two Kingdomes, as by two diſtinct bodies acting ſingly, but <hi>they were united by ſolemn Covenant made to Almighty God and by League each to other, as one intire body to proſecute this cauſe;</hi> Which was the expreſſion uſed by the honourable Houſes in their
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:137407:6"/>Declaration of the 5 of Auguſt 1645, to the Lords States Generall of the United Provinces of the Low Countrys. In which Declaration this notable inſtance was given, which deſerveth alſo to be remembred, That by the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant both Houſes of Parliament and many thouſands of other His Majeſties Subjects of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſtand bound aſwell as wee, to hinder the ſetting up of the Church government by Biſhops in the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> And that wee aſwell as they ſtand bound to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the extirpation thereof in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> And as by the Covenant, the Kingdomes are faſt linked together in the whole proſecution of this cauſe; ſo parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly both are oblieged to endeavour mutually to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties Perſon and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, in the preſervation and defence of the true Religion, and liberties of the Kingdomes, That the world may bear witneſſe with our conſciences of our loyalty, And that we have no thoughts or intentions to diminiſh His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties juſt power and greatneſſe.</p>
            <p>From the Treaty the ſame thing doth further appeare, it being thereby manifeſt, that as our Army was to be lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vied for the common good of both Kingdomes in the purſuance of the ends expreſt in the Covenant, And not as, Auxiliaries for the ſingle good of this Kingdom; So they are not tyed to be ſubject to the reſolutions, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections of either Kingdome ſingly, but of both joyntly. Alſo by the 8th. article, no Ceſſation, Pacification nor Agreement for Peace whatſoever, is to be made by either Kingdome, without the mutuall advice and conſent of both. So that if the diſpoſall of the Kings Perſon men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the vote of both Houſes, be intended for the good, Peace, and ſecurity of both Kingdomes, then it
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:137407:7"/>ſhould not be done without the mutuall advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of both; But, if intended for the Peace and ſecurity of this Kingdome within it ſelf ſingly, this were to ſettle the Peace of the one Kingdome, not only without the councell and conſent, but before the ſetlement of the other, and ſo the more inconſiſtent with the plain ſcope of that Article. Moreover by the 9th. Article of the ſame Treaty, all matters of difference ariſing between the Subjects of the two Nations, are to be reſolved and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined by the mutuall advice and conſent of both, which hath ever been the uſuall way in ſuch caſes: Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther know we any other way for healing of differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two free Nations, which are as Brethren and equalls, and neither of them ſubordinate to the other. If therefore any difference ſhould ariſe (which God forbid) between the two Parliaments or any others of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of the two Nations, concerning the diſpoſing of His Majeſties Perſon, then the queſtion cannot be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe reſolved and determined, but by the mutuall advice and conſent of both. How much better is it (according to the 6fh. Article of the Covenant) to conſult how to prevent all differences which are like to ariſe between us or our poſterities?</p>
            <p>The honourable Houſes in their wiſdome did think fir that in the managing of this warre, there ſhould be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the Councells of both Kingdomes reference to the Engliſh aſwel as to the Scottiſh forces. How much more may we expect a conjunction of Councells in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of His Majeſties Perſon, wherein the one King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is as much intereſted, as the other.</p>
            <p>If more need to be ſaid in this buſſineſſe, we hope it is not forgotten, how the Declarations of both Houſes and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:137407:7"/>their Commiſſioners ſent into <hi>Scotland,</hi> to deſire their aſſiſtance and engagement in this Warre, did invite, ſollicite and perſwade that Nation upon principles of common intereſt, And in regard the one Kingdome can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enjoy a firme and durable peace, while the other is in warre: Wee were alſo put in minde of the affection and duety which becometh brethren. And as we did upon theſe and the like conſiderations, eſpouſe our brethrens quarrell; So it cannot be offenſive that we deſire from them an improvement of the very ſame principles: And that the ſame meaſure of the Conjunction of intereſts be given to us, which was got from us. God forbid, that wayes of ſeparating the intereſts of the Kingdoms ſhould now be ſtudied, as much as wayes of Uniting them were before endeavoured. We cannot but expect better things from our Brethren, then in their proſperity to deſert us, who did engage and Joyn with them in their greateſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction; Or to think of ſecuring their own Peace without us, while the troubles of our Kingdome continue.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, wee cannot chooſe but obteſt by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good of both Kingdomes; by the conjunction and parity of intereſts; by the love of Brethren; by Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of both Houſes; by former preſidents; by the Treaty between the Kingdomes; by the ſolemn League and Covenant: yea, by the very law of Nations and rules of common equity, that there may be a conjunction of the Councells and reſolutions of both Kingdomes, in diſpoſing of that royall Perſon who is King of both, and that all lawfull and poſſible means (of which this is one and a chiefe one) may be uſed, which may preſerve His Majeſties Perſon, honour, and happineſſe according to the Covenant; Monarchicall government according to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:137407:8"/>fundamentall lawes of both Kingdomes: Together with a firme and happy Union between the Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Theſe principles we deſire ſtill to goe upon, And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if the vote of both Houſes communicated unto us, be underſtood as a materiall demand of His Majeſties Perſon to be delivered unto them, to be diſpoſed of as they ſhall think fit: This as it doth not neceſſarily follow from the words of the vote nor doth agree with that ſenſe of the vote, which in charity we are moſt willing to entertain, ſo there are juſt and great reaſons againſt it. We acknowledge that we are not to preſume the worſt, but the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the intentions of the honourable Houſes towards the King. But wee do not doubt it will be mutually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged that for preventing of differences afterwards, it is moſt fit and neceſſary, that there be a cleere and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct underſtanding between the two Kingdomes, in a buſineſſe of this nature and conſequence. And that it is not to be expected from private perſons (though un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der juriſdiction) much leſſe from another Kingdome, that they ſhould paſſe from their intereſt or juſt ſecurity, becauſe they have to doe with ſuch, as they judge to be honeſt and faithfull. To ſpeak therefore to the nature of the thing in it ſelf, if the Scots Army ſhould deliver up His Majeſties Perſon without his owne conſent, and that upon the vote communicated unto us, which (although it may ſuffer a benigne interpretation and be underſtood of the diſpoſing of the Kings Perſon favourably and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably, yet) as the words ſtand, is comprehenſive and capacious of more then is fit to be expreſſed: This Act of the Army were not agreeable to their Oath of Alleageance (obliging them to defend his Majeſties perſon from all harms and prejudices) nor to the Solemne League and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:137407:8"/>Covenant, which was not intended to weaken, but to ſtrengthen our Alleageance, and to wipe off the calumny and aſperſion of Rebellion: For which end, before our engagement in this Warre, it was mutually covenanted between the Kingdoms, to preſerve the Kings Majeſties Perſon and Authority, in the preſervation of the Religion and Liberties of the Kingdoms; Thereby holding forth to the world, that the preſervation and defence of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Liberties, may well conſiſt and was intended to conſiſt with the preſervation of his Majeſties Perſon and Authority, whom therefore our Army cannot deliver, to be diſpoſed of by any others, at pleaſure. This delivery were alſo inconſiſtent that joynt, equall, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon intereſt of both Kingdoms in the diſpoſall of his Majeſties Perſon, which we have before aſſerted; And, were upon the matter a paſſing from the right and intereſt of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> int that buſineſſe. It were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo contrary to his Majeſties power of reſidence in any of his Kingdoms, and to the free exerciſing of the duties of his place and acts of perſonall government, ſuch as the hearing and redreſſing of the grievances of his Subjects in Parliament, and his concurring to the making of Laws. Neither could it ſtand with the Commiſſions given to the Committee of Eſtates and general Officers of our Army, or with their Military Oath, to deliver up their King without his own conſent, and without warrant from the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to be diſpoſed of by another Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Even as it were not to be expected, that the Army under the command of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> if they were in <hi>Scotland</hi> for our aſſiſtance there, in the like cauſe, and under the like ingagements, in a receſſe of the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> and without their warrant, would upon the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:137407:9"/>like demand deliver up the King (having caſt himſelf in their hands) to be diſpoſed of by the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Finally, if it be contrary to the Law and common practiſe of Nations, to deliver up the meaneſt Subject fled to them, though it be for the greateſt crimes (for which cauſe the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> in the 4. of King <hi>James,</hi> as likewiſe in the large Treaty, refuſed a generall Act of remanding between the two Kingdoms, unleſſe they ſhould be united into one) how much more would the world abroad condemne our Army for a baſe and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable act, if they ſhould deliver up their Head and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign (having caſt himſelf into their hands) to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of at the arbitrement of another Nation.</p>
            <p>And now we hope it will not be teadious, that we fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enlarge our ſelves, upon this great ſubject, by adding ſatisfactory Anſwers to ſuch Objections, as have been, or may be made againſt our deſires and Principles in this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>Object. 1. <hi>That the Scottiſh Armie is an Auxiliarie Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of</hi> England, <hi>and under their pay, and therefore ought to deliver up the King, to be diſpoſed of by both Houſes as they ſhall think fit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is ſufficiently known, that the Scottiſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie came not into this Kingdom in the nature of Auxilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: For when it was deſired by the Parliament of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> that the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould ſend an Auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarie Army into this Kingdom, to be ſubject to the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and reſolutions of both Houſes, It was abſolutely refuſed, as may appear by the ſeverall Papers about that purpoſe yet extant. The Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee and conſider, how prejudiciall it was to forſake their own Peace, and what infinite troubles, loſſes, and unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:137407:9"/>danger their engagement with the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> againſt ſo powerfull and prevailing an Enemy, would bring upon the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland:</hi> And as they regarded not the large offers, nor the threats of the other ſide for all their proſperity; ſo there was no offer of pay or other worldly advantage whatſoever from the Houſes of Parliament, which could have induced them to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take ſo hazardous and deſperate a War. It was the good of Religion, King, and Kingdomes, they ſet before their eyes, in order to which end, they accounted nothing too dear unto them: And having reſolved to engage in this Cauſe for aſſiſtance of their Brethren therein, they did not ſtand upon conditions, But without reſpect to the ſeaſon of the yeer, the great ſtrength of the Enemy, and other diſcouragements; They did in a ſhort time leavy an Army at their own charge: And becauſe of the many burdens then lying upon this Kingdom, were content for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to accept of a ſum toward the Monethly entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that Army, amounting to little more then half pay, and to ſuperſede all further recommence, till the War ſhould be at an end. And ſeeing the Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was to quite their own Peace, and equally with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to undergo the hazard of the War, it was found rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that the proſecution thereof, and the making of the conditions of Peace after the Warre, ſhould be with joynt advice and conſent of both Kingdoms. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe grounds, a Covenant was agreed upon for the Reformation of Religion, and for preſervation of the Liberties of the Kingdoms, and of the Kings Perſon and Authority: together with a Treaty, wherein it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared that the Scottiſh Army ſhall be commanded by a Generall appointed by the Eſtates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſhall be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:137407:10"/>ſubject to ſuch reſolutions and directions, as are and ſhall be mutually agreed upon and concluded between the Kingdoms, or their Committees in that behalf appointed for purſuance of the ends of the Covenant: of which, one is to defend and preſerve his Majeſties Perſon.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>That the King is in</hi> England, <hi>and therefore to be diſpoſed of by both Houſes of Parliament, and cannot be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of by the Scottiſh Army: And though the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland <hi>may pretend to an intereſt and power in the diſpoſing of the King, yet they can have no exerciſe of that power in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: <hi>And albeit the Scottiſh Army, according to the Treaty between the Kingdomes be only ſubject to ſuch reſolutions, as are mutually agreed upon by both Kingdomes, or their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittees appointed in that behalf, yet this is only to be underſtood in ordering and regulating of the Scottiſh Forces for proſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the warre, and the Treaty extends no further.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Although His Majeſties riding one dayes journey, might wholly ſubvert the grounds of this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection; Yet wee ſhall not inſiſt upon this anſwer, becauſe we conceive it toucheth not the true ſtate of the queſtion. It hath been already cleered what is not, and what is the ſtate of the queſtion, which being remembred wee doe aſſert, that the King comming voluntarily to the Scottiſh Army, they cannot in duety deliver him againſt his will to the Houſes of Parliament without conſent of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Scotland:</hi> For the being in <hi>England</hi> takes not away the relation between the King and His Subjects of the Kingdome of <hi>Scotland,</hi> nor ought it to impede the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the mutuall dueties founded upon that relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: For alledgeance hath no limitation of place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing grounded upon the Law of Nature aſwell as the law Municipall, and ſo is rather univerſall then locall. The
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:137407:10"/>difference of plate takes not away the relation and mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all dueties between parents and children, And it is not the place but the relation which gives intereſt to the diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of the Perſon of the King. As his being in <hi>England</hi> takes not away the relation between him and his Subjects of <hi>Scotland,</hi> ſo it doth not infringe the mutuall obligations and ſolemn engagements between the Kingdomes, for joynt counſells in proſecution of the War and ſettling of the peace: The Kings coming to the Scottiſh Army, being an emergency of our joynt warre, and the right diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſall of his Perſon, the onely meane (for the preſent) of our joynt ſecurity and peace. Neither can the Kings being in <hi>England,</hi> prejudge any right or priviledge of either Kingdome. It is the fundamentall right and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the liberty of that Kingdome (as wee acknowledge it to be the right and priviledge of the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi>) that the perſon of their King ought not to be diſpoſed of, but with their advice and conſent. The place of the Kings reſidence (as was anſwered to us, when in the large Treaty it was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired His Majeſty might ſometimes reſide in <hi>Scotland</hi>) is at his own election, in either of the Kingdomes as the exigence of affairs ſhall require and he ſhall think fit, Or elſe muſt be determined by the mutuall advice and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of both Kingdomes. From all which grounds it is apparent, that the Kingdom where he reſides for the time, may doe no Act which may hinder His Majeſty to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the office and duety of a King, to the Kingdom, from which he is abſent in Perſon, Nor impede him to repair to that Kingdome, when the affairs thereof ſhall neceſſarily require it. Otherwiſe, if the Kingdome where His Majeſtie reſides hath the ſole intereſt and right to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:137407:11"/>of His Perſon, the Eſtates of the Parliament of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> might upon former occaſions and may now, in caſe the King and Prince ſhall repair to <hi>Scotland,</hi> lawfully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain them there, and make it the place of the ordinary re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence of them and their poſterity, without the conſent of the Kingdome of <hi>England:</hi> Which we acknowledge could not be done without a manifeſt prejudice and injury to this Kingdome. Wherefore we cannot but conclude that whereſoever the King be, in <hi>Scotland</hi> or <hi>England,</hi> he being the King of both, ought to be diſpoſed of for the good and with the conſent of both Kingdomes. And if it be conſidered that the Scottiſh Army was invited and called into this Kingdome by both Houſes in a Treaty for proſecuting the ends of a ſolemne League and Covenant, whereof one is to preſerve and defend His Majeſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, there can remaine no doubt concerning the exerciſe of that right and intereſt in this Kingdome: And therefore it ſeems very ſtrange, that when upon invitation they are come into <hi>England,</hi> as for other ends, So to defend His Majeſties Perſon, their being in <hi>England</hi> ſhould be made uſe of, as an argument why they ſhould deliver up the Perſon of their King to be diſpoſed of, as both Houſes ſhall think fit. Whereas it is alledged, that the Treaty ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends no further then to the ordering and regulating of the Scottiſh Forces in relation to the warre: Although this be really anſwered from the nature of the thing, the Kings coming to the Scottiſh Army being an emergency of the warre, and ſo the delivering of His Perſon comes under the regulation and direction of both Kingdomes or their Committees, as an Act of the Scottiſh Army; Yet that all doubt may be removed, wee further adde, that it is cleere from the third Article of the Treaty, that the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:137407:11"/>Scottiſh Army is to receive the Directions of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms or of their Committees, in all things which may concern the purſuance of the ends of the Covenant and Treaty, whether in relation to Peace or Warre. In the 8th Article of the Treaty, no Ceſſation, Pacification, or agreement for Peace whatſoever, is to be made by either Kingdom, or the Army of either Kingdom, without the advice and conſent of both Kingdoms. And in the 9th Article, all differences ariſing between the Subjects of the two Nations are to be reſolved and determined by the mutuall advice and conſent of both Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>Object. 3. <hi>That the Scottiſh Armie did carry away the King from the Leaguer before</hi> Newark <hi>when there was a Committee of both Houſes there, without ſeeking their conſent; and that they have ſince diſpoſed of him without conſent of the Houſes of Parliament, whereas by the Treatie they ought to do nothing without a joynt reſolution of both Kingdoms or their Committees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No ſooner did the King come into the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Army, but the very ſame day the Committee of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> reſiding with that Army, did acquaint the Commiſſioners of both Houſes therewith: And not ſatisfying themſelves with this, the day following they wrote a Letter to the Committee of <hi>Scotland</hi> reſiding at <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> and another to the Committee of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms here (which was communicated to both Houſes) deſiring the advice of this Kingdome, as in a matter of common intereſt, and declaring they would obey the joynt reſolutions of both Kingdoms: Yet no anſwer or advice was returned unto them, either from the Houſes or their Commiſſioners. But immediatly after the ſurren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Newark,</hi> they received information that five thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:137407:12"/>Horſe and Dragoons from Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax</hi> his Army were upon their March towards them Northward (which the honourable Houſe of Peers was pleaſed to give order to ſtop) there being no Enemy in thoſe parts to be oppoſed: Upon conſideration whereof, the Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters wherein they had ſtayed during the ſiege of <hi>Newark,</hi> being extreamly exhauſted, and the Service for which they came thither being performed, for preventing miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes or new troubles between the Kingdoms, They, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved into <hi>Tork ſhire,</hi> and the King as he came unto them of his owne accord, did voluntarily March along with them. Upon ſeverall occaſions afterwards, They and we did earneſtly deſire the honourable Houſes to ſend a Committee, to joyn and co-operate with the Committee of Eſtates there upon the place, in all things according to the Treaty: But no anſwer was returned. And from time to time the Houſes were acquainted with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in that Army; which, were according to the Covenant, and the known reſolutions of both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, to debarre all ſuch of both or either Kingdoms as had been in Arms againſt the Parliament, from coming into their Quarters, or to the Court, or to the Kings Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, according to the deſire of the Houſe of Peers. And whereas it is affirmed, That by the Treaty the Scottiſh Army ought to do nothing without a joynt reſolution of both Kingdoms or their Committees, There is no ſuch Clauſe in the Treaty, but they are to be ſubject to ſuch reſolutions as are and ſhall be agreed upon, and concluded mutually between the Kingdoms or their Committees, as by Ordinance of Parliament, the Army under the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Earle of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> or of Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> was to receive and obſerve the Directions of the Committee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:137407:12"/>of both Kingdoms ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter;</hi> But in caſe no new Directions were ſent unto them, they were left to former Orders (if any were) or otherwiſe to their own judgement and diſcrection. There was never any ſuch reſolution agreed upon between the Kingdoms or their Committees, as that the Scottiſh Army ſhould not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the King if he came unto them, but it is an agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment between the Kingdoms (in the Covenant) that they ſhould preſerve and defend his Majeſties perſon; And (in the Declarations of both Kingdoms) to reſcue him from the common Enemy: So that the Scottiſh Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie having often deſired to know the direction and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Houſes of Parliament, concerning the King, and no new Directions being ſignified unto them; Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Treaty they were to obſerve the Directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Reſolutions formerly agreed upon between the Kingdoms. And as the Scottiſh Army do and will ever acknowledge that they claim no power to diſpoſe of the Kings Perſon, but are ſubject to, and ſhall be ready to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low low whatſoever both Kingdoms ſhall agree upon, as beſt for the King and Kingdoms: ſo their keeping and p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving his Majeſties Perſon (as they would do to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his eminency and relation in an Army or Garriſon Town) without the leaſt thought of hindering his volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary return to his Parliament, cannot be reputed or called a diſpoſing of his perſon.</p>
            <p>Object. 4. <hi>If any Peere of</hi> England <hi>go to the Scottiſh Armie and deſire their Protection, can he not be diſpoſed of without the conſent of the Committee of Eſtates of the Kingdom of</hi> Scotland <hi>reſiding with that Army?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There is a wide and manifeſt difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the relation the Scottiſh Armie hath to any Subject
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:137407:13"/>of <hi>England,</hi> and the relation they have to their King: which are ſufficiently diſtinguiſhed in the third and fourth Articles of the Covenant: for by the one they are mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually obliged to preſerve and defend his Majeſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and by the other they are mutually obliged to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, that all Incendiaries and dividers betwixt the King and his people, or betwixt the Kingdoms, be brought to tryall and condigne puniſhment before the ſupream Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories of the Kingdoms reſpectively, And the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> hath equall right and intereſt with the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>England</hi> in the diſpoſal of the Perſon of the King, which they cannot pretend unto concerning the Perſon of any Subject of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. 5. <hi>That ſeeing it is alleadged by us, that the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of the Kings Perſon comes in place of a Peace, then the receiving of the King into the Scottiſh Armie without conſent of the Houſes, is aequivalent to the making of a Peace, without conſent of the Kingdome of</hi> England, <hi>contrary to the eighth Article of the Treatie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It hath been ſufficiently anſwered before, that the Scottiſh Army neither hath nor will take upon them to diſpoſe of the King. He came unto them without Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitulation or Treaty, his reſidence with them is voluntary and free, and they do nothing which may hinder him to come to his Houſes of Parliament. But if the kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> ſhould conſent to the deſire of the Houſes, that they may have the ſole diſpoſall of the Perſon of the King, It being that which comes in the place of the Peace and ſecurity of both kingdoms, They will really quite the right and intereſt they have by the eighth Article of the Treaty, concerning the making of a Peace; for which ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever of the kingdoms is acknowledged to have the ſole
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:137407:13"/>diſpoſall of the King, may without the other make Peace with him, when, how, and in what terms they pleaſe.</p>
            <p>Object. 6. <hi>That</hi> England <hi>is a free Nation, and in former times it was in the power of the Parliament of</hi> England <hi>to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of their Kings, And if one Kingdome pretend to a joynt right of diſpoſing of the King, while he is in the other, it is to entrench upon the former liberty of that Kingdome. That the Kingdome of</hi> Scotland <hi>have no reaſon to diſtruſt the Houſes of Parliament, who when the King ſhall be in their power, will not diſpoſe of him otherwiſe then may conſiſt with their duety, according to the Covenant and Treaty between the Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We will not diſpute what power the Houſes of Parliament formerly had to diſpoſe of the Perſon of their King; but whatſoever power or right they have, the like is due to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland,</hi> And ſo the Perſon of the King being common to both and indiviſible, cannot be diſpoſed of, but by conſent of both kingdoms. It were another queſtion indeed if it were as in former times, if we had different Kings, if there were not an Union of the kingdoms under one head and Monarch, if there were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Covenant nor Treaty between the kingdoms; But ſince all theſe are, and that the peace and ſecurity of both kingdomes, is ſo much concerned in the diſpoſall of the King; not any one of them without the other, can juſtly pretend to the ſole judgement and right, to determine what is beſt and moſt expedient for the ſafety and ſecurity of both. Nor can it in reaſon be made an argument that the one Kingdome diſtruſts the other, becauſe the one will not renounce and reſigne all right and intereſt they have in the perſon of the King, and matter of their own ſecurity and peace, to the judgement and determination of the other; otherwiſe, according to this Argument,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:137407:14"/>where there is any truſt, there ſhould be no contract be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween perſon and perſon, nor Treaty between Nations; Or if there be any Treaty or agreement, the performance or not performance of it, is to be left to arbitrement. But we cannot ſee that this doth argue any diffidence or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt truſt more then when private perſons lending money to the Publike, deſire ſecurity, and will not depend upon pleaſure. And therefore, though it is not to be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but the houſes of Parliament would diſpoſe of the Perſon of the King ſo as might conſiſt with their dutie, in performing the Covenant and Treaty; Yet, this can be no argument why the Scottiſh Armie ſhould neglect their dutie, or the kingdome of <hi>Scotland</hi> quite the intereſt and right they have in the perſon of the King.</p>
            <p>Object. 7. <hi>That the King is in the poſſeſsion of the Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Armie, and though a joint advice and conſent of both Kingdoms be urged for his diſpoſall, Yet if the Houſes of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament agree not to what</hi> Scotland <hi>ſhall deſire, the King doth ſtill remain in the power of the Scotts Armie, and ſo the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of</hi> England <hi>hath no conſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If this argument were turned over, the ſtrength or weakneſſe of it may the more eaſily appear: Suppoſe the King were here at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> it may be upon the ſame grounds urged, that the kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi> would have no conſent in his diſpoſall, And ſo much the more that the Houſes claime the ſole intereſt and judgement to diſpoſe upon the Kings Perſon, which we deſire may be done joyntly, as may be beſt for the ſecurity and ſafety of both kingdoms. And we ſee no reaſon, why it may not now be determined when he is in the Scottiſh Armie (who are intruſted by both, and ſubject to the reſolution of both kingdoms) as well as heereafter, ſince he came
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:137407:14"/>thither of his own accord, and his reſidence there is vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary. And if his Majeſtie ſhall think fit to repair hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to his Houſes of Parliament, they ſhall do no act which may either hinder or diſſwade him, but cannot conſtrain him, or deliver him to the Houſes to be diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of as they ſhall think fit.</p>
            <p>It may now abundantly appear from the grounds and conſiderations before expreſſed, that the Scottiſh Armie may not deliver up his Majeſties Perſon, to be diſpoſed of by the one Kingdom, without the conſent of the other; Upon ſuppoſition whereof, we ſhall in the next place (without preſuming to preſcribe wayes, or impoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions) expreſſe our ſelves concerning ſome expedients, which in reference to his Majeſtie, deſerve to be looked upon, conſidered of, and compared together; where we ſhall onely premiſe this much, That whatever way ſhall be taken, if the right end be looked at, his Majeſties Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ought to be ſo diſpoſed of, as may ſerve moſt for the ſafety and happineſſe of the King himſelf, and for the common Peace and ſecurity of the Kingdoms, United in this Cauſe by the ſolemn League and Covenant; And, as may beſt agree with their dutie, Covenant, and Treaties.</p>
            <p>Theſe ends being before our eyes, although it be moſt eligible and beſt of all, that His Majeſtie ſhould without further delay, forthwith give ſatisfaction in the Propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Peace (which hath been with all inſtancy preſſed, not only by us, but by all the judicatories of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland</hi>) and ſo returne fully reconciled to His Houſes of Parliament; Yet, ſince (to our unſpeakable grief) this this hath not been as yet obtained; Wee doe propoſe that His Majeſties coming to <hi>London,</hi> or to ſome of his houſes neer <hi>London,</hi> with ſafety, freedome and honour (which
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:137407:15"/>is deſired by himſelf, that hee may be heard, And that upon the cleering of his doubts, he may knowingly give a ſatisfactory anſwer to the Propoſitions) is much better then the other wayes which may be expected in caſe this His Majeſties deſire be not agreed unto. As for His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties going to <hi>Ireland</hi> or other-where beyond Sea, It could not be the way to a preſent peace now ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired; but would certainly prognoſticate new troubles. Laſtly, His Majeſties coming hither, or neer this place, is a more probable and hopefull way to preſerve the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Kingdomes, becauſe the Enemy being ſtill in Armes in <hi>Scotland</hi> and expecting ſupplies from <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Kingdome diſabled by their great ſufferings to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaine an Army for ſuppreſſing the malignant party, It were much more eaſie to raiſe new Forces there to the diſturbance of the peace of this Kingdome; then it could be here, where (by the bleſſing of God) all the Forces and Garriſons of the Enemy are ſubdued, and where it will not be ſo difficult to hinder delinquents from acceſſe to His Majeſty. The dangers and inconveniencies of any of theſe other wayes, do ſo much preponderate, and the preſent condition of affairs doth ſo much differ from that time, when both Houſes with our concurrence did diſagree from His Majeſties deſire of comming to <hi>London</hi> (at which time he had both Garriſons and field Forces unreduced) that it may be conceived not only ſafe, but (as things ſtand) moſt convenient, to agree to His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties coming to <hi>London</hi> or neer it, upon ſuch conditions and aſſurances from him, as ſhall be by joynt reſolution found neceſſary for preventing the acceſſe of delinquents to His Majeſtie, or any inteſtine commotion, or forraine invaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the diſturbance of the peace of either Kingdome.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:137407:15"/>We truſt it might accelerate a happy peace, bring the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent differences to an end, and be no grief of heart after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, if upon ſuch terms and conditions, both Houſes ſhould be pleaſed to revive and renew ſuch an invitation and aſſurance upon their part, as was contained in their anſwer to His Majeſties Meſſage of the 11. of Septemb. 1642. where, after mention made of their chief grievance; it was added. <hi>All this notwithſtanding, as we never gave your Majesty any juſt cauſe of withdrawing your ſelfe from your great Councell, So it hath ever been and ſhall ever be farre from us to give any impediment to your returne, or to neglect any proper means of curing the diſtempers of the Kingdom, and cloſing the dangerous breaches betwixt your Majeſty and your Parliament, according to the great truſt which lies upon us. And if your Majeſtie ſhall now be pleaſed to come back to your Parliament without your Forces, we ſhall be ready to ſecure your royall Perſon, Crown, and dignity with out lives and fortunes; Your preſence in this great Councell, being the only means of any Treaty betwixt your Majeſty and them with hope of ſucceſſe.</hi> Divers ſuch paſſages there are in the Declarations of both Houſes which we ſhall not need to mention.</p>
            <p>But if the Houſes of Parliament ſhall not agree to His Majeſties deſire of coming hither with ſafety, freedome, and honour; We offer to be conſidered in the next place; whether it be not expedient, that once again Commiſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners be ſent to His Majeſty in name of both Kingdomes, with power to hear his deſires, and to endeavour the ſatisfaction of doubts and ſcruples; with intimation alſo, That if His Majeſtie ſhall not give ſatisfaction in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, both Kingdomes will without any more ſuch applications, conſult and joyntly reſolve upon other wayes of their ſafety and ſecurity. And upon the other
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:137407:16"/>part, that if His Majeſty will be now at laſt graciouſly pleaſed, to ſatisfie the deſires of both Kingdoms, His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Throne with his juſt power and greatneſſe, ſhall be eſtabliſhed, aſwel as the peace and ſecurity of his Subjects.</p>
            <p>All which we doe propound in a brotherly freedome, not being peremtorily wedded or addicted to any expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent that we have offered; but, if the honourable Houſes in their wiſdome, ſhall be pleaſed to think of any other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, which ſhall bee for the good, ſafety, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the King and Kingdomes, We ſhall be moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ready to agree unto it, when it ſhall be made known unto us, not doubting but that in the faithfull and conſcionable uſe of all good and poſſible means, which may prevent differences between the Kingdomes, there will be at laſt a ſweet and brotherly agreement in ſuch a concluſion, as ſhall be good in Gods eyes, and wherein both Kingdomes ſhall finde greateſt comfort and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By command of the Commiſsioners for the Parliament of</hi> Scotland. <hi>Jo. Cheiſlie.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:137407:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
